Letting go; just observing
How are you?
You told us to let go.
It seems to be similar to observing
the anger rising. But it isn't the same
so I would like to know the difference.
What are the differences between letting
go and just observing the anger rising.
To analyze 'just observing quietly
one's anger rising' means
when we encounter
the actions or words of another,
for example, what our eyes see,
hear with our ears,
smell with our noses or
taste with our tongues
can be to our liking or not.
Or they can be neutral to our feelings.
When these emotions arise,
we can get whirled into the feelings.
If we like them, we want to keep them
forever wanting to hold onto them.
This is called clinging.
If we don't like them,
we want to avoid them.
If we neither like nor dislike them,
there arises the hesitation.
Then our actions ensue;
we say or do something.
So, when we can't get the things we want
we get distressed.
or when we can't get rid of those
we dislike, we also get distressed.
It is not only the bad feelings
cause us to suffer.
We get distressed
by the good feelings also.
We want to possess
what makes us feel good.
If we obtain what we want, we get
satisfied but if not we are in distress.
When we hate something we want
to avoid it; we want to abandon it.
But if we can't avoid it,
we feel miserable.
What we like or dislike,
what we want to do or hate to do,
these are called feelings,
emotions or desires.
But we often get swayed by these desires.
We get engrossed in these desires.
But if we look at it a bit more carefully,
even though we may want something
or want to do something,
we can get disparaged by others.
If a woman grabs a man
just because she likes him,
she can be accused of
a sexual harassment.
If I eat something just because I want to
eat it, it can be harmful to my health.
If we say something because we want to,
we can be disparaged and criticized.
So, a wise person refrains from
doings things he wants to.
Or do the things he doesn't want to.
It is more advantageous to be
behaving this way.
It prevents loss and brings the benefit.
One is not controlled by one's feelings.
The desires can be resisted.
So, when the anger rises in us,
we are asked to notice that
and not to become angry.
As the desires arise, instead of following
the desires, we notice them
and not follow through with
words and behaviors.
But normally, we are easily whirled into
our desires once they arise.
We don't even get to notice
the feelings arising,
they just turn into words and actions.
So, an emotional person will express
his likes or dislikes into words directly.
So, in order to maintain the equanimity
when such desires and feelings arise
we are told to calmly
observe the feelings.
But if one has already put into actions
the feelings and the desires risen within,
then one is already engrossed
in the fury of the passion.
So not getting caught by the feelings
arising, just watching them calmly
will dissipate them.
You will not fall into the emotional
grip. You just observe the feelings.
This is, however, after the event already.
If we investigate this further,
our feelings do not arise
in the contact with the outside world.
Our bodies and mind react to the feelings
when we make contact with outside world.
Before the emotions arise,
there is a feeling.
It is either pleasant or unpleasant.
When a pleasant feeling arises,
we like it.
but the unpleasant one we dislike.
So, the emotions of likes and
dislikes do not arise first;
pleasant or unpleasant arises first.
The emotions of likes and dislikes
follow the feelings of pleasant or not.
If we can notice the
feelings arising first,
we can hinder the progression
to emotional state.
We must not let them rise to
the emotional state of like and dislikes.
But it is not about repressing
or suppressing of the emotions.
The pleasant or unpleasant feelings
rise and fall by themselves.
So we do not assign
our likes and dislikes onto our feelings.
That is Vipassana
or the mindfulness practice.
Broadly, by observing the feelings,
but not proceed to the level of
emotional likes and dislikes
thereby maintaining the calm and
clear mind is the fundamental principle.
If the emotion is aroused already,
then just notice the feeling of
likes and dislikes
so that you are not controlled
by the emotions.
If already in the grip of the emotions,
realize that
but not move onto
the outward expressions.
If you have already expressed them,
realize that you have done so.
Then you repent right away.
So, observing something means that
we notice the risen state as it is.
however it is,
without discussing whether it is right or
wrong, good or bad, front or back.
Whatever arises,
we notice it as it arises as it is.
But when the minute a feeling dissipates
but the emotions are aroused
in short, a craving has risen, then it is
a bit difficult to control the impulse.
In the grip of full fledged desire, it is
hard to restrain even if you notice it.
Even with noticing, you have to
suppress actively.
It is very difficult to control this.
So, be aware of what has risen and
notice right away and be remorseful.
Notice, "Oh, I have become angry" and
be remorseful.
So, noticing/observing means
to be aware of
moment to moment state
of your mind and behaviors.
You can notice what has happened already
and be observant.
Noticing/observing that is.
Then, what is the letting go?
It is about why you are becoming angry.
Observing is to be aware of you
becoming angry, right?
Then, what is the cause of this anger?
This is about the cause.
Observing is in regards to
the rising of anger.
Letting go has to do with
the cause of this anger.
There is a reason for
this anger to arise.
The reason is the thought,
"I am right and the other is wrong."
So as the anger arises, if you are
able to recognize it and know that
you are now in the grip of
this thought of being right
which is the cause for the anger.
Then, you drop
this thought of being right.
This letting go is not about
letting go of the anger.
By observing what arises yet
not being entranced by it,
letting go is the result of noticing
the cause of this arousal.
The result might be the same but
there are some differences in the process.